Hoffman Family Papers
© 2006 University of Connecticut
Hoffman Family Papers.
undated, 1933-1998.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Center.
Hoffman Family.
9 linear feet.
The principal members of the Hoffman family present in the collection are John and Florence Hoffman; Abbie, Jack, and Phyllis, their children; Rose Shanberg, Florence's sister; and Anita Hoffman, Abbie's second wife. Other family members that appear in the collection include Joan Hoffman, Jack's wife; Sheila, Andrew, and Ilya "Amy" Hoffman, Abbie's first wife and children; america, Abbie and Anita's son; and Johanna Lawrenson, Abbie's common-law wife.
MSS19990106
Biography
Abbot Howard Hoffman ("Abbie") was born November 30, 1936 in Worcester, Massachusetts. He studied psychology with Abraham Maslow at Brandeis University, where he graduated in 1959 with a B.A. He then completed a year of graduate work at the University of California at Berkeley. His growing participation in the various counter-culture movements led to his arrest and subsequent trial as a member of the Chicago 7 following the 1968 riots at the Democratic National Convention. He co-founded the Yippie movement and was a vocal activist for civil rights, ending the Vietnam War, and other social movements. Following his arrest for selling cocaine in 1973, he jumped bail and spent the next seven years as a fugitive, sometimes traveling abroad while continuing to write and protest before reemerging in 1980. After serving a brief jail term, Abbie continued to write both articles and books, work with community groups in organizing local protests, and visit campuses to speak with students about taking civil and political action until his death in April of 1989.
Abbie Hoffman authored numerous articles and books. His works include: Revolution for the Hell of It, 1968, Woodstock Nation, 1969, Steal This Book, 1971, Vote (co-authored with Jerry Rubin and Ed Sanders), 1972, To America with Love (co-written with Anita Hoffman), 1976, Soon to be a Major Motion Picture, 1980, Square Dancing in the Ice Age, 1982, Steal this Urine Test (co-authored with Jonathon Silvers), 1987, Preserving Disorder: The Faking of the President (co-written with Jonathon Silvers), 1988, and The Best of Abbie Hoffman (co-edited with Daniel Simon), 1989.
Jack Hoffman was born September 13, 1939 in Worcester, Massachusetts. Following two years of service with the U.S. Army Medical Corps, Jack took over the family business, Worcester Medical Supply Co., from his father. Jack participated in various demonstrations and campaigned actively for the election of Eugene McCarthy in 1968 and Shirley Chisholm in 1972.
Anita Hoffman, who became Abbie's second wife on June 8, 1967, accompanied Abbie during many of his protests and demonstrations but was left behind to care for their son, america, when Abbie jumped bail in 1974. In 1976 she published a series of letters they exchanged to keep in touch entitled "To America with Love."
Rose Shanberg, Abbie and Jack's maternal aunt, left a diary describing her struggles as a young college student and the effect of her brother Abraham's untimely death.
Scope and Content
The correspondence consists mainly of letters either from or to Abbie, Jack, or Florence, their mother. Also included are numerous sympathy cards to the Hoffman family following Abbie's death. While the family papers contain items of the family's private side, it also includes evidence of their participation in political campaigns and research for books and articles. The collection of written work focuses on Abbie's work and his life. The bulk of the collection consists of copies of government records, newspaper stories, and magazine articles. Both the New York City Police Department and the Federal Bureau of Investigation maintained extensive records of Abbie Hoffman's activities. In addition to numerous news articles about Abbie, there is substantial coverage of the 1988 presidential elections. Artifacts include awards, political pins and posters, and clothing Abbie often wore for speeches, demonstrations, or on his book covers. Audio/visual material include two cassettes with friends and supporters reading Abbie Hoffman's work, a reel of Abbie Hoffman's interview with Connie Chung, and various 16mm films of Hoffman family vacations and events. Most of the photographs are family photographs taken from scrapbooks.
Organization
The collection consists of family correspondence, article research and personal papers, written material by and about Abbie Hoffman, copies of government files and newspaper articles, 16 mm films of the family, and personal photographs.
Series I: Correspondence (undated, 1971-1995) is divided amongst the three main participants; Abbie, Jack, and Florence Hoffman. One other significant part is the condolence cards following Abbie's death. The letters are filed chronologically, with undated letters in the front of the file.
Series II: Family Papers (undated, 1953-1994) This series contains two groups. Papers related to the personal life of the family are arranged alphabetically first, followed by a group of papers that seem to be research material for articles and books, also organized alphabetically.
Series III: Written materials (undated, 1933-1996) are clearly divided between those written by Hoffman family members and other authors. The papers are organized alphabetically first by author, then by title. The collection includes work from Abbie, Anita, and Jack Hoffman, as well as the diary of Rose Shanberg, Abbie and Jack's aunt. Drafts of Jack Hoffman's biography of his brother entitled Run, Run, Run: The Lives of Abbie Hoffman which evolved under numerous working titles including "Abbie: One Step Ahead", "Abbie: Three Steps Ahead", "A Brother's Story", "Dear Abbie", and "Three Moves Ahead..." are included here. Drafts, manuscripts, interviews, and program scripts about Abbie Hoffman and his work, including copies of various Yippie pamphlets, are arranged alphabetically.
Series IV: Government Documents (undated, 1965-1980) and Series V: Newspaper and Periodical Clippings (n.d, 1936-1997) include records from the FBI, NYCPD, and other police reports have been arranged chronologically. Multiple dates often appeared on individual papers, so papers were organized with the latest date mentioned internally within the document itself, not simply stamped or written on the page. Newspaper and periodical clippings were arranged chronologically.
Series VI: Artifacts (undated, 1955-1998), Series VII: Audio/Visual Materials (undated), and Series VIII: Photographs (undated, 1944-1989). Large posters have been stored in the Oversize area. Cassette tapes and 16mm home movies have been grouped topically. Included with the family photographs are photocopies of original family photos not found in the collection.
Related Material
Archives and Special Collections has significant holdings reflecting the underground, alternative and counter cultures emerging in the United States during the 1960s and 1970s. For further information on specific holdings, please contact the curator.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized topically and alphabetically or chronologically.
Separated Material
The following newspapers and magazines were originally part of the collection. Where possible, pertinent articles were photocopied and placed within the collection before the originals were removed. Most of the issues are stored in their entirety either on microform at the Homer Babbidge Library (HBL) or within the Alternative Press Collection kept in the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center. Copies of the Atlanta Journal-Constitution, Campaigns & Elections, Chicago History, High Times, National Lampoon, New York Post, New York Press, Parade, People, Philadelphia Intelligencer/Record, Saturday Night, USA Today are available through interlibrary loan on microform.
For information on specific issues of these titles originally held in the collection, please contact the curator.
Abbie Hoffman at Vanderbilt 1999-0106.vr2
Bibliography
Becker, Theodore and Anthony Dodson. Live this Book: Abbie Hoffman's Philosophy for a Free and Green America. Chicago, IL: Noble Press, 1991.
Hoffman, Jack and Daniel Simon. Run, Run, Run: The Lives of Abbie Hoffman. New York, NY: G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1994.
Jezer, Marty. Abbie Hoffman, American Rebel. New Brunswick, NJ: Rutgers University Press, 1992.
Raskin, Jonah and Eric Foner. For the Hell of It: The Life and Times of Abbie Hoffman. CA: University California Press, 1997.
Sloman, Larry. Steal this Dream: Abbie Hoffman and the Counterculture Revolution Against America. New York, NY: Bantam Books, 1998.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Hoffman, Abbot Howard.
Subjects:
Chicago Seven.
Document Types:
Correspondence.
Occupations:
Activist.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection in its entirety was donated by Jack Hoffman.
Accruals
Additional materials were donated in 2001 but have not yet been processed and integrated into the collection.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1971-1995
  - CBS Re-Creation Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 1:1)
  - FBI -- Jack Hoffman Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 1:2)
  - "Steal This Urine Test" Correspondence, undated (Box 1:3)
  - Correspondence to Abbie Hoffman, 1982-1989 (Box 1:4)
  - Correspondence from Abbie Hoffman, undated (Box 1:5)
  - Correspondence from Abbie Hoffman, 1966-1988 (Box 1:6)
  - Correspondence to Florence Hoffman, undated,-1989 (Box 1:7)
  - Correspondence to Jack Hoffman, undated-1989 (Box 1:8)
  - Correspondence to Jack Hoffman, 1990-1994 (Box 2:9)
  - Correspondence from Jack Hoffman, undated-1992 (Box 2:10)
  - Other Correspondence, undated (Box 2:11)
  - Other Correspondence, 1971-1995 (Box 2:12)
  - Sympathy Cards (1), 1989 (Box 2:13)
  - Sympathy Cards (2), 1989 (Box 2:14)
  - Sympathy Cards (3), 1989 (Box 2:15)
- Series II: Family Papers, undated, 1953-1994
  - Abbie Hoffman Webpage, undated (Box 3:16)
  - Autopsy of Abbie Hoffman, 1989 (Box 3:17)
  - Crayon Cards, undated (Box 3:18)
  - Ephemera. Includes facsimile of American flag donated by Jon Howard, signed by David Dellinger, Abbie Hoffman, Allen Ginsberg, and William S. Burroughs, undated (Box 3:19)
  - Financial Records, undated (Box 3:20)
  - "Flip the Bird" Calender, 1994 (Box 3:21)
  - Legal Documents (1), undated (Box 3:22)
  - Legal Documents (2), undated (Box 3:23)
  - Notebook. Black vinyl 1981 Monthly Minder. 8 pgs., 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Notebook. Blue-green vinyl book with gold leaf. Book of Memories which contains names of friends and relatives who attended Abbie's funeral services, undated (Box 6)
  - Newsletters, undated (Box 3:24)
  - 1972 Chisholm Campaign, 1972 (Box 3:25)
  - Political Pamphlets, undated (Box 3:26)
  - Post Cards, Ad Cards, undated (Box 3:27)
  - Résumés Jack Hoffman, 1989-1991 (Box 3:28)
  - School Records of Abbie Hoffman, 1953-1955 (Box 3:29)
  - Speaking Schedules for Abbie Hoffman, 1987-1988 (Box 3:30)
  - Book Excerpts, undated (Box 3:31)
  - CIA Trial Papers, 1987 (Box 3:32)
  - 1988 Election Notes, 1988 (Box 3:33)
  - "The Gulf War: A Study of the Media..." Lewis, Jhally, Morgan, 1991 (Box 3:34)
  - Indices, undated (Box 3:35)
  - Prozac Studies (1), 1988-1990 (Box 3:36)
  - Prozac Studies (2), 1988-1990 (Box 3:37)
  - Prozac Studies (3), 1988-1990 (Box 3:38)
  - Manic-Depressive Research, 1987-1990 (Box 3:39)
  - Marriage Law Research, 1990 (Box 3:40)
  - Reagan-Bush Hostage Deal Research, 1988-1991 (Box 3:41)
  - Riots Research, undated (Box 3:42)
- Series III: Written Materials, undated, 1933-1996
  - Advertisements, undated (Box 3:43)
  - Book Covers, undated (Box 3:44)
  - Abbie Hoffman
    - "Abbie Hoffman? Leaving the Movement?" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1971 (Box 3:45)
    - "Abbie Hoffman's Fugitive Life" Article Abbie Hoffman, undated (Box 3:46)
    - "Abbie Hoffman's Plains Speaking" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:47)
    - "America on $0 a Day" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1971 (Box 3:48)
    - "Border Crossings" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1979 (Box 3:49)
    - "Did You Hear the One..." Article Abbie Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:50)
    - "The Eyes of Conkrite" Essay Abbie Hoffman, 1973 (Box 3:51)
    - "The Great Gourmet Rip-Off" Essay Abbie Hoffman, 1981 (Box 3:52)
    - "How Clifford Irving Stole..." Article Abbie Hoffman, 1972 (Box 3:53)
    - "How Clifford Irving Stole..." Article Abbie Hoffman, 1984 (Box 3:54)
    - "I Confess" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1979 (Box 3:55)
    - "I Remember Papa" Drafts Abbie Hoffman, 1976 (Box 3:56)
    - "Letter From Abbie Hoffman" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1968 (Box 3:57)
    - "Loch Ness Nellie..." Article Abbie Hoffman, 1976 (Box 3:58)
    - "Love Letters From the Underground" Article Abbie and Anita Hoffman, 1976 (Box 3:59)
    - "My Life on the Lam" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:60)
    - National Student Convention Speech Abbie Hoffman, undated (Box 3:61)
    - "1978: Part of the World..." Article Abbie Hoffman, 1978 (Box 3:62)
    - "Nuclear Waste Upstate" Essay Abbie Hoffman, 1982 (Box 3:63)
    - "Origens and Rebuttal" Essay Abbie Hoffman, undated (Box 3:64)
    - "President Jimmy: The Outside Story" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:65)
    - "Reefer Madness" Essay Abbie Hoffman, 1987 (Box 3:66)
    - "Shoot-Out in Tinseltown" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1976 (Box 3:67)
    - "Steal This Author" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1974 (Box 3:68)
    - "Too Soon the Hero" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:69)
    - "The Underground Odyssey..." Article Abbie Hoffman, 1982 (Box 3:70)
    - Untitled Essays Abbie Hoffman, undated (Box 3:71)
    - "Village of the Bomb" Article Abbie Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:72)
    - Soon to be a Major Motion Picture Draft, undated (Box 3:73)
    - Steal This Urine Test Research, undated (Box 3:74)
    - Steal This Urine Test Notes, undated (Box 3:75)
    - Steal This Urine Test Drafts, undated (Box 3:76)
  - Anita Hoffman
    - "Life Without Abbie" Article Anita Hoffman, 1974 (Box 3:77)
    - "What Six Nice People..." Article Anita Hoffman, 1977 (Box 3:78)
  - Jack Hoffman
    - Abbie: One Step Ahead Draft Jack Hoffman, undated (Box 3:79)
    - Abbie: Three Steps Ahead Draft Jack Hoffman, undated (Box 3:80)
    - A Brother's Story Book Proposal Letters, undated (Box 3:81)
    - A Brother's Story Notes (1), undated (Box 3:82)
    - A Brother's Story Notes (2), undated (Box 3:83)
    - A Brother's Story Chapter Outline Proposals, undated (Box 3:84)
    - A Brother's Story Chapter Outline Drafts, undated (Box 3:85)
    - A Brother's Story Sample Chapter Drafts, undated (Box 3:86)
    - A Brother's Story Front Matter, undated (Box 3:87)
    - Dear Abbie Draft Jack Hoffman and Andrea Fine, 1989 (Box 3:88)
    - "Life of Jack Hoffman" Essay Jack Hoffman, undated (Box 3:89)
    - Three Moves Ahead... Draft Jack Hoffman and Andrea Fine, 1989 (Box 3:90)
  - Rose Shanberg
    - Diary (1) Rose Shanberg, 1933-1935 (Box 3:91)
    - Diary (2) Rose Shanberg, 1933-1935 (Box 3:92)
  - Other Authors
    - "Abbie! A Celebration" Program Outline, 1989 (Box 4:93)
    - Abbie Hoffman: Prophet from Worcester (2) Manuscripts Michael Boover, 1993 (Box 4:94)
    - Abbie Hoffman: American Road Story Manuscripts Al Giordano, undated (Box 4:95)
    - "Abbie, I'm Glad I Knew Ye" Essay, undated (Box 4:96)
    - American Rebel: A Political Biography... (2) Manuscripts Marty Jeezer, 1989 (Box 4:97)
    - "Author's Kit" Jeremy P. Tarcher, Inc., undated (Box 4:98)
    - "The Baptism of Brandeis" Article Jon Landau, 1969 (Box 4:99)
    - Barnyard Epithet... J. Anthony Lukas, 1970 (Box 4:100)
    - Best of Abbie Hoffman (1) Manuscript Daniel Simon, 1989 (Box 4:101)
    - Best of Abbie Hoffman (2) Manuscript Daniel Simon, 1989 (Box 4:102)
    - Best of Abbie Hoffman (3) Manuscript Daniel Simon, 1989 (Box 4:103)
    - Best of Abbie Hoffman (4) Manuscript Daniel Simon, 1989 (Box 4:104)
    - Book Reviews, undated-1992 (Box 4:105)
    - CBS Re-Creation Script, 1989 (Box 4:106)
    - "Conspiracy: The Trial of the Chicago 8" Outline HBO Showcase, 1987 (Box 4:107)
    - "Dear Abbie!! A Celebration..." Program Notes Ram's Horn Productions, 1990 (Box 4:108)
    - "In Hiding-An Interview with Abbie Hoffman" Transcript Ron Rosenbaum, 1975 (Box 4:109)
    - "Interviews: Abbie Hoffman" Interview John Schultz, 1989 (Box 4:110)
    - Jewish Mothers' Hall of Fame Excerpt Fred Bernstein, 1986 (Box 4:111)
    - Jonah Raskin Title Pages (2) Signed by Abbie Hoffman, undated (Box 4:112)
    - "The Last Yippie" Interview and Article Howard Goodman, 1994 (Box 4:113)
    - Live This Book Manuscript Becker and Dodson, 1991 (Box 4:114)
    - "Making of a Yippie" Draft Nancy Shapiro, undated (Box 4:115)
    - Motion Will Be Denied Excerpt John Schultz, 1972 (Box 4:116)
    - "The Movie Isn't Over Yet" Article John Schultz, 1989 (Box 4:117)
    - New Hope: Life and Times of Abbie Hoffman (2) Drafts Jonah Raskin, 1996 (Box 4:118)
    - "Revolution for the Smell of It" Interview Steve Kraus, undated (Box 4:119)
    - Typed Notes Tony Dodson, undated (Box 4:120)
    - Underground Chapter and Reviews Jonah Raskin, 1978 (Box 4:121)
    - "Urine Testing and the Fourth Amendment" Draft Kevin Zeese, undated (Box 4:122)
    - Yippies' Anti-War Propaganda (1), undated (Box 4:123)
    - Yippies' Anti-War Propaganda (2), undated (Box 4:124)
    - Yippies' Anti-War Propaganda (3), undated (Box 4:125)
    - Yippies' Anti-War Propaganda (4), undated (Box 4:126)
  - Collected Written Works
    - Brandeis 1958 Yearbook, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Catalog of Out-Of-Print Yiddish Books. Amherst, MA: National Yiddish Book Center, Spring 1988 (Box 6)
    - Epstein, Jason. "The Trial of Bobby Seale." Reprint, The New York Review of Books., 1969. (Box 5)
    - Fulton, Kenneth, ed. Democrats in Convention, 1972., Democratic National Convention Committee, 1972. (Box 5)
    - Hollander, Nicole. "Mercy, it's the revolution and I'm in my bathrobe." (Box 6)
    - Jezer, Marty, ed. "Tactics and Strategies for the Peace Movement: Where Do We Go From Here?" A.J. Muste Memorial Institute Discussion Series ., no. 1. 1985. (Box 5)
    - Learning Alliance., (September 1994-February 1995). (Box 5)
    - Life: John F. Kennedy Memorial Edition. 1963. (Box 5)
    - "The Year in Pictures." Life: Special Report 1973., 1974. (Box 5)
    - "The Magazine." The Creative Writing Class of Danvers Alternative High School. (Box 5)
    - Manville, Nancy, ed. Hair: The American Tribal-Love Rock Musical. Natoma Productions, 1968. (Box 5)
    - National Lampoon. Vol. 1, no. 7. (October, 1970). Photocopy found in collection. (see box 8, folder 177) (Box 5)
    - 1989 Danvers Alternative High School Yearbook. (Cover features dedication to Abbie Hoffman). (Box 5)
    - Odyssey: Creative Alternatives in Criminal Justice. (Fall 1990). (Box 5)
    - Odyssey: Creative Alternatives in Criminal Justice. (Spring 1992). (Box 5)
    - Robert P. Walker Enterprises. (lecture agency advertisment booklet features Jack Hoffman). (Box 5)
    - Sane World/Freeze Focus. Winter 1987, vol. 26, no. 4, p. 1-16. Annotated copy found in collection. (see box 8, folder 195) (Box 5)
    - Street Guide Greater Worcester. Boston: Interstate Publishing Co., 1961.. (Box 6)
    - Tierney, Tom Ronald Reagan: Paper Dolls in Full Color, New York: Dover Publications, Inc., 1984. (Box 5)
- Series IV: Government Documents, undated, 1965-1980
  - Article Index (1), undated (Box 4:127)
  - Article Index (2), undated (Box 4:128)
  - FBI Document Requests, undated, [1. list of files along with notes of files marked for destruction (no date); 2. Jack Hoffman request from FBI with FBI note of deleted pages (1991)] (Box 4:129)
  - NYCPD File, undated, [1. Alonso Russell appointed to Board of Director of Operation Breakthrough, list of names of New Haven residents (presumably linked to Operation Breakthrough); 2. news articles - New York Times and New York Daily News, five men arrested for bombing plot in New Haven - linked to Operation Breakthrough; 3. New York Civil Liberties Union (NYCLU) complaint concerning police brutality at the 1967 demonstration against Secretary of State Dean Rusk with personal testimonies, Hoffman's testimony focuses on police brutality after his arrest; 4. news articles - Columbia University Spectator, Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) involvement in demonstration against Secretary of State Dean Rusk; 5. NYPD surveillance notes for the April 1968 MOBE anti-war demonstration; 6. police report with an accompanying description of the meeting and specifics for the April 1968 MOBE anti-war demonstration; 7. NYCPD list of participating organizations and signs present at the protest; 8. National Black Anti-War Anti-Draft Union letter in support of the demonstration; 9. letter to marchers concerning procedure and plans for the demonstration from the organizers; 10. "Mother Do Not Allow Your Son to Die in Vietnam" - NYCPD notes anti-imperialist Puerto Rican nationalist organization; 11. list of organizers, names of SDS leaders (Ted Gold, Mark Rudd, Jeff Gordon, Jeff Jones); 12. note of a confirmation at the Dumas Hotel in New York City; 13. note containing list of the names of organizers (Tom Hayden, Jeff Gordon, etc.); 14. Anti-Complicity Movement newsletter; 15. anti-war flyers (student and general); 16. 5th Avenue Peace Committee document on themes of the demonstration; 17. April 27th anti-war demonstration flyers and April 26th international student-faculty strike flyers, May Day; 18. Student Mobilization Committee to End the War in Vietnam (MOBE) document containing strike endorsements from all over the world; 19. news article - Student Mobilizer Vol. 2 No. 2 March 1st; student strike and anti-war march April 26th-27th (Box 4:130)
  - Police Reports (1), undated, [1. unidentified agent or agency, report on the March on the Pentagon October 22, 1967; 2. police report on the March on the Pentagon with a list of radicals, includes Jerry Rubin but not Abbie Hoffman; 3. Solutions to Employment Problems (STEP) from National Association of Manufacturers (NAM), "Dimensions of the Problem" program for addressing high school dropouts and unemployment; 4. NYCLU report on March 22nd YIP-in at Grand Central Station in New York City, complaints of police brutality; 5. unidentified agent or agency (probably NYCPD); police notes, mentions East Side Service Organization (ESSO), a social service agency for young drop-outs, mainly hippies; 6. unidentified agent or agency (probably NYCPD); report on Youth International Party (YIP) with a list of common activities; 7. unidentified agent or agency (probably NYCPD), police notes on YIP tactics; 8. NYCPD, police account of a YIP demonstration on August 22nd 1967 (photographs); 9. Commanding Officer, Bureau of Social Services to Commanding Officer Information Unit, request for information regarding licenses; 9. Lansing, Michigan PD to NYCPD; information regarding a stolen registration] (Box 4:131)